<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<p:activity xmlns:p="urn:www.develop.com:terra:activity:v1">

  <name>Deployment</name>
  <duration>45</duration>
  <workDir>deployment</workDir>

  <goals>
    <goal>Deploy assemblies to the Global Assembly Cache (GAC).</goal>
    <goal>Configure version policy to redirect versions at load-time.</goal>
    <goal>Configure an application to find assemblies from alternative locations.</goal>
    <goal>Deploy an application via ClickOnce</goal>
  </goals>

  <overview>
    <p>In this activity you will work with the simple Mandelbrot fractal viewer shown below:</p>
    <p>
    <image src="fractalexplorer.jpg"/>    
    </p>


    <p>The goal of this activity is to work with field-replacement and version
    redirection in a semi-realistic environment. In the screenshot above the actual
    Mandelbrot rendering is performed by a DLL (<strong>DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot.dll</strong>)
    which is hosted by the application (<strong>FractalExplorer.exe</strong>).  In this
    activity you will compile FractalExplorer.exe against version <strong>1.0.0.0</strong>
    of DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot.dll. This code works, but not all that well.  You will find
    two additional implementations of DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot.dll that enhance the 
    basic functionality of 1.0.0.0 (exactly how is left to you to discover).  The goal
    here is to compile the original application and then swap in different implementations
    of DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot.dll <strong>without recompiling FractalExplorer.exe!</strong> 
    This is similar to what you might want to do in a production environment where
    the FractalExplorer has already been deployed and you want to give users the option
    of updating to the new library.</p>

    <p>The working directory for this exercise is
       <filelink href="deployment/" target="new">work\deployment\</filelink>. There is 
       very little code in this activity so there's no need for the usual "before" and
       "after" directories.  Instead you will be experimenting with deployment and
       config file settings.</p>
  </overview>

  <parts>

  <part optional="false">
    <name>Getting started</name>
    <description>
    <p>First you need to get familiar with the application</p>
    </description>

    <steps>
    <step>
    <p>Open <filelink href="deployment/fractalexplorer.sln">FractalExplorer.sln</filelink> in 
    the <strong>work</strong> directory.  You'll find three projects inside:</p>
    
    <p><strong>DevelopMentor.Fractals.DLL</strong> provides basic math support
    needed for complex number manipulation.</p>
    <p><strong>Mandel1</strong> provides version 1.0 of the mandelbrot
    rendering functionality. If you examine the project properties you'll
    see that this project compiles to a DLL named <strong>DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot.dll</strong></p>
    <p><strong>FractalExplorer.exe</strong> provides basic window management
    as well as a dialog box that will display assembly information for all assemblies
    loaded by the application.</p>
    </step>
    
    <step><p>Compile and run <strong>FractalExplorer.exe</strong> as-is.  Open a few child
    windows and play with them. You may want to use the <strong>Configuration</strong> button
    to adjust the <strong>MaxIterations</strong> property - higher values will generate more
    detail, but will take a correspondingly long time.</p></step>
    
    <step><p>Now use <strong>File | Deployment Info...</strong> to bring up a dialog box that
    displays information about the DLLs that FractalExplore.exe depends on. Pay attention to
    the <strong>Location</strong> and <strong>Codebase</strong> values as well as the <code>Expected</code>
    and <code>Loaded</code> values of the loaded assemblies. The most interesting DLL here
    is <strong>DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot</strong> which should be selected already.</p></step>
    </steps>

    <solutions>
    </solutions>

<!--  <samples>
    <sample>dotnet.runtime.assemblies.CodeBaseRedirect</sample>
    <sample>dotnet.runtime.assemblies.PrivatePath</sample>
  </samples> -->

  </part>

  <part optional="false">
  <name>Deploying to the GAC</name>
  <description><p>In order to enable easy selection between versions you will now deploy
  <strong>DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot.dll</strong> to the GAC.</p></description>
  <steps>
    <step><p>Bravely try dragging DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot.DLL from the file system to
    the GAC by dragging it into <strong>c:\windows\assemly</strong> using the shell.  You
    should get an error saying that the DLL doesn't have a strong name.</p></step>
    <step><p>
    So, you need to give a strong name to the <strong>Mandel1</strong> project. You can do this
    by selecting <code>Mandel1</code> in the Solution Explorer and choosing properties (either
    via right clicking or via the "Properties" button in the upper left of the Solution Explorer).
    </p></step>
    
    <step><p>
    Now go to the "Signing" tab and select the "Sign the Assembly" check box.  Click the corresponding
    combo box and choose "New...".  This will bring a dialog where you can create a new keyfile; use
    <strong>keys.snk</strong> as the name. You can protect it with a password if you want, but it's not
    necessary here.
    </p></step>
    
    <step><p>
    Now try to build the solution. You should see this error:
    </p>
    <p type="code">error CS1577: Assembly generation failed -- Referenced assembly 'DevelopMentor.Fractals' does not have a strong name</p>
    
    <p>Strongly-named assemblies can only reference other assemblies if they have strong names as well.  So, use
    the steps outlined above to give a strong name to <code>DevelopMentor.Fractals.dll</code>.  Note that you
    do <strong>not</strong> need to use the same keyfile - you can generate a second pair of keys for this 
    DLL if you like.</p>
    </step>
        
    <step><p>
    Now you are ready to put <code>DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot.DLL</code> into the GAC.  Add it to the GAC
    and run the application, looking at the assembly info.  You should see a very different location and
    codebase now for the DLL.
    </p></step>
    
    <step><p>The application you are
    running may work now, but in general when you put an assembly in the GAC you should put all dependant
    assemblies in the GAC as well; otherwise other applications would fail if they didn't have 
    <code>DevelopMentor.Fractals.dll</code> in their local directory. Add <code>DevelopMentor.Fractals.dll</code>
    to the GAC as well before moving on to the next part.
    </p></step>
    
  </steps>
  </part>

  <part optional="false">
  <name>Version redirection</name>
  <description><p>Now you will experiment with version policy to swap in versions 2.0.0.0
  and 3.0.0.0 without changing the original EXE.</p></description>
  <steps>
    <step><p>
	To swap in a new version you have to tell the runtime which assembly you're swapping
	out and which version you want to replace it with.  This is done via config files, so
	the main thing you'll have to do here is author the appropriate config file.    
    </p></step>

    <step><p>
    First things first - you need a new version to swap in. Open <filelink href="deployment/mandel2/mandel2.sln">mandel2.sln</filelink>
    and build it.  Note that you will need to sign version 2.0.0.0 with the <strong>same</strong>
    keypair you generated in the previous part of the lab. Add version 2.0.0.0 to the GAC and 
    verify that the GAC now contains two versions of the <strong>DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot</strong>
    assembly.
    </p></step>

    <step><p>
    Now you need to create a configuration file for FractalExplorer.exe.  The easiest way to 
    do that for this lab is to reopen <filelink href="deployment/fractalexplorer.sln">FractalExplorer.sln</filelink>
    and add a config file to the FractalExplore.exe project. (Right click on the project and choose
    <strong>Add... | New Item</strong> and choose <strong>Application Configuration file</strong>).
    Using the example in the slides create a config file that redirects the <strong>DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot</strong>
    assembly to version 2.0.0.0.  (You will need to know the public key token for the key you used
    to sign the assembly - you can get it by running the application and using the "assembly deployment information"  
    dialog box).  A sample config file is shown below (note that config files are case-sensitive
    and very sensitive to XML namespace usage).
    </p>
    <p type="code" mode="collapsable">
    <![CDATA[
<configuration >
  <runtime>
    <assemblyBinding xmlns="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:asm.v1" >
      <dependentAssembly>
        <assemblyIdentity 
                name="DevelopMentor.Mandelbrot" 
                publicKeyToken="be418bc72a93105f" />
        <bindingRedirect oldVersion="1.0.0.0"
                             newVersion="2.0.0.0" />
        </dependentAssembly>
    </assemblyBinding>
  </runtime>
</configuration>
    
    ]]>
    
    </p>
    </step>

    <step><p>
    Now build and run <strong>FractalExplorer.exe</strong> again (note that the only reason to
    "build" here is to get the app.config file deployed).  If you use File | New to create a new
    fractal it should look different and behave a bit differently.
    </p></step>
  </steps>
  
  </part>


  <part optional="false">
    <name>Deploying with ClickOnce</name>

    <description>
      <p><strong>ClickOnce</strong> makes it easy to deploy applications in an XCOPY fashion,
      but allows clients to get auto-downloading and auto-updating as well as integration with
      the Start Menu and the "Add/Remove Programs" dialog. In this section
      you will deploy your application via ClickOnce.</p>
    </description>

    <steps>
      <step>
      <p>Start by deleting <strong>app.config</strong> so that <strong>FractalExplorer</strong> goes
      back to using v1.0.0.0 of the Mandelbrot DLL. ClickOnce doesn't support GAC installation, 
      so version redirection doesn't make sense - if you want a new version of a lib 
      in your ClickOnce app just publish the new version and clients will download it.</p>
      </step>
      <step><p>
      Next you need to generate an x.509 (Authenticode) certificate for the project.  This will 
      be used to sign the <strong>manifest</strong> files used by ClickOnce. You can generate a
      new test certificate on the <strong>Signing</strong> tab of the project properties. Check
      the <strong>Sign the ClickOnce manifests</strong> checkbox then click 
      <strong>Create Test Certificate</strong>. This should generate a new file named
      <strong>FractalExplorer_TemporaryKey.pfx</strong></p>
      </step>
      <step>
      <p>
      Now use the Publish wizard to do a simple ClickOnce deployment. Start the
      wizard by choosing <strong>Build | Publish FractalExplorer</strong>.
      </p>
      </step>
      <step>
      <p>The wizard will suggest a local IIS deployment, just accept the default and 
      choose <strong>Next &gt; </strong></p>
      </step>
      <step>
      <p>The second step in the wizard asks <strong>Will the application be available offline?</strong>
      Go ahead and accept the default (yes) and continue.</p>
      </step>
      <step>
      <p>Press Finish to kick off the deploy. The application will build
      and files will be pushed out to a virtual directory called <strong>FractalExplorer</strong>.
      Once the wizard is done it will launch IE, which should look about like this:</p>
      <p><image src="publish.jpg"></image></p>
      </step>
      <step>
      <p>Open <strong>c:\inetpub\wwwroot\FractalExplorer</strong> and examine the files there. In particular
      you should look for <strong>FractalExplorer.Application</strong> and 
      <strong>FractalExplorer.Manifest</strong>. Inspect these files just to get a
      sense of them (probably the easiest thing to do is to copy the files and give them
      a <strong>.xml</strong> extension, then view them in IE).</p>
      </step>
    </steps>
    
  </part>

  <part optional="true">
    <name>Installing ClickOnce Applications on a client</name>

    <description>
      <p>Now you will see the client side of ClickOnce installation.</p>
    </description>

    <steps>
      <step>
        <p>To install a ClickOnce application you surf to the <strong>application manifest (.application)</strong>
        file. Since you already have <strong>publish.htm</strong> up you can just click on the <strong>Install</strong>
        button.</p>
      </step>
      <step>
        <p>You should get prompted with a warning that <strong>Publisher cannot be verified</strong>. This is because
        the app has been signed with a temporary X.509 test certificate and not a "real" certificate.  If you click
        on <strong>"More Information..."</strong> you should see that the application is asking for FullTrust which is 
        a bit silly for this application.  Nevertheless you should be able to click "OK" and the app will install and
        run.  You should also see a new Start menu item that you can use to launch the application. Try closing and 
        running the application from the start menu.
        </p>
      </step>
      
      <step>
        <p>
        Verify that the application files were downloaded by looking in 
        <strong>%userprofile%\Local Settings\Apps</strong>.
        Can you find your application files?
        </p>
      </step>
    </steps>
  </part>

  <part optional="true">
    <name>Deploying a new version</name>

    <description>
      <p>Now that your app is installed and your clients have subscribed you can push out a new
      version</p>
    </description>

    <steps>
      <step>
        <p>Remove the <strong>Mandel1</strong> reference from the  <code>FractalExplorer</code> project. 
        Add <strong>Mandel3</strong> to your solution and reference it from FractalExplorer. Run it
        in the debugger and verify that version 3.0.0.0 runs.</p>
      </step>
      <step>
      <p>Publish the application again but <strong>do not click "install" on publish.htm</strong>. Instead
      just run the application from the <strong>Start</strong> menu.  What happens?</p>
      </step>
    </steps>
  </part>
  
  
  <part optional="true">
    <name>Uninstalling ClickOnce Applications</name>

    <description>
      <p>ClickOnce-deployed applications can be reverted to a previous state or uninstalled from the Control Panel.</p>
    </description>

    <steps>
      <step>
        <p>ClickOnce-deployed apps can be uninstalled from Control Panel. 
        Uninstall the application using the familiar <strong>Add or Remove Programs</strong> dialog.  Verify that doing so deletes the files in 
        <strong>%userprofile%\Local Settings\Apps</strong>.</p>
      </step>
    </steps>
  </part>
  
  </parts>



<!--
  <samples>
    <sample>dotnet.runtime.assemblies.policy</sample>
  </samples>
-->

<!--
  <howtos>
    <howto>dotnet.runtime.delegates.DefineADelegate</howto>
  </howtos>

  <samples>
    <sample>dotnet.runtime.value-types.structfun</sample>
  </samples>
-->

  <quizzes>
    <quiz>dotnet.runtime.assemblies-overview</quiz>
  </quizzes>  
</p:activity>
